Preliminary Guide to the James Cannon Papers, 1869-1989
James Cannon papers 1869-1989
Cannon, James, 1864-1944
16.27 Linear Feet 12,159 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Acquired
Biographical Note
Methodist clergyman from Virginia, journalist, and leader in the prohibition movement. Also known as James Cannon, Jr.
Collection Overview
Collection contains diaries, correspondence, reports, minutes, journals, articles, legal papers, pamphlets, obituaries, and other papers. Main interests center on the material reflecting Cannon's part in the presidential campaign of 1928; his activities in various state, national, world, and religious temperance associations, the General Conference and the Virginia quarterly conferences of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, and Methodist missionary enterprises. Other papers pertain to his leadership in the effort to unify the northern and southern branches of the Methodist Church. Correspondents include Harry F. Byrd, Carter Glass, Josephus Daniels, Cordell Hull, Herbert Hoover, Frank Knox, William G. McAdoo, H.L. Mencken, Collins Denny, Gerald P. Nye, Warren A. Candler, Charles Evans Hughes, John R. Mott, Edwin D. Mouzon, Claude A. Swanson, Woodrow Wilson, Charles C. Carlin, Charles Curtis, Walter F. George, Andrew Mellon, Robert F. Wagner, William Hodges Mann, and G.W. Ochs-Oakes.
Addition (2011-0101) (103 items, 0.2 lin. ft.; dated 1902-1945 and undated) contains publications and printed materials written by Cannon and others. Topics include prohibition, Methodism, Catholicism, politics, and the international peace movement.
Incomplete index to the collection included.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Methodist Episcopal Church - Clergy
Methodist Episcopal Church - Missions
Prohibition - Societies, etc.
Presidents - United States - Election - 1928
Methodist Church - History
Temperance - United States - Societies, etc.
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series
  - 1869-1912 (Box 1)
  - 1913-1920 (Box 2)
  - 1921-1922 (Box 3)
  - 1923-1924 (Box 4)
  - 1925 (Box 5)
  - 1926 (Box 6)
  - 1927-1928, Aug. (Box 7)
  - 1928, Sept.-Dec. (Box 8)
  - 1929, Jan.-Aug. (Box 9)
  - 1929, Sept.-Dec. (Box 10)
  - 1930 (Box 11)
  - 1931, Jan.-May (Box 12)
  - 1931, June-Oct. (Box 13)
  - 1931, Nov.-1933 (Box 14)
  - 1934 (Box 15)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 16)
  - 1937-1941 (Box 17)
  - 1942-1955, undated (Box 18)
- Writings Series
  - 1888-1922 (Box 19)
  - 1923-1927 (Box 20)
  - 1928-1944, undated (Box 21)
  - Autobiography (early drafts--Chapters I-III) (Box 22)
  - Autobiography (early drafts--Chapters IV-VI, Misc.) (Box 23)
  - Autobiography (typed copy--Chapters I-VI) (Box 24)
  - Autobiography (typed copy--Chapter VII; carbon copy--Chapters I-V) (Box 25)
  - Autobiography (carbon copy--Chapters VI-VII) (Box 26)
  - Addresses, statements, biographical sketches, and press releases (Box 27)
  - Sermons (Box 28)
- Printed Material Series
  - undated (Box 29)
  - undated (Box 30)
- Clippings Series
  - 1887-1924 (Box 31)
  - 1925-1928 (Box 32)
  - 1929 (Box 33)
  - 1930 (Box 34)
  - 1931 (Box 35)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 36)
- Clippings Series
  - 1933-1936 (Box 37)
  - 1937-1949 (Box 38)
  - undated (Box 39)
- Pictures Series
  - James Cannon, Jr., et. al. (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 41)
- Volumes Series
  - undated (Box 42)
- Oversize Material Series
  - Pictures, undated (Opaperfolder OC:I:5)
  - Certificate of Ordination to Episcopal Church (Opaperfolder OC:I:8)
  - Christian Herald Distinguished Religious Service Award
- Accession (2011-0101)
  Addition (2011-0101) (103 items, 0.2 lin. ft.; dated 1902-1945 and undated) contains publications and printed materials written by Cannon and others. Topics include prohibition, Methodism, Catholicism, politics, and the international peace movement.
  - 1902-1945 and undated (Box 43)